Jason Ash

jason@ashanalytics.com

Profile

Data scientist and actuary with advanced financial modeling, forecasting, and analytical expertise. Experience managing teams to monitor complex risk, operate financial hedging programs, improve operational and marketing processes, and develop and launch new business initiatives. Seeking to contribute to a team by identifying valuable strategic improvements using analytical and predictive models.



2016

2014

Professional Designations

Fellow of the Society of Actuaries (FSA), Corporate Finance and Enterprise Risk Management concentration

Chartered Enterprise Risk Analyst (CERA) Member of the American Academy of Actuaries (MAAA) 2013

An FSA is earned after passing eight rigorous exams (40% pass rate each) and completing additional Elearning courses and modules. Most candidates take 6-10 years of post-graduate self-study to finish.

Open Source

pyesg, Economic Scenario Generator for Python

2019 - Present

pyesg is an open source stochastic scenario generator built for Python. Inspried by the scikit-learn API, users can create stochastic models, generate thousands of real-world or risk-neutral scenarios, or fit models with historical market data.

Publications

2017 "<u>Creative Landscape</u>" — featured article in <u>The Actuary</u> magazine "Bayesian Models in Insurance" — presenter at Predictive Analytics Symposium 2019 "Improving Actuarial Communication" — presenter at Valuation Actuary Symposium 2018 2017 -Personal blog — www.jtash.com — learned html and css to build a custom blog from scratch Present

Work

Founder at Ash Analytics

San Francisco, 2017 - Present

Experience

Ash Analytics provides actuarial and analytic consulting services.

- Advising startups on business model, unit-ecomomics, and value proposition
 - Built projection models to forecast user and revenue growth, assessed total addressable market, tested sensitivities to product pricing
 - Created pitch decks, and advised on venture funding strategies
- Data and Analytics consulting for Fortune 500 companies
 - Worked with a major ridesharing company to improve data capture and analytics
 - Worked with insurance companies to modernize actuarial work: built pricing models and predictive analytics models for new products
- Open source programming and projects
 - <u>pyesg</u>, an open source economic scenario generator
 - Built a real-time data streaming platform to analyze energy data

Head of Insurance and Analytics at Leaplife

San Francisco, 2017 - 2018

Leaplife is an insurtech startup backed by RGA, one of the largest reinsurance companies in the world. Leaplife is developing advanced models to improve life insurance distribution and product development.

- Built a data warehouse by querying APIs, organizing, and linking all company data for comprehensive analysis
 - Marketing data from Facebook ads manager, Google Adwords, Amazon advertising, and others
 - Customer data from CRM platforms Prosperworks and Hubspot
 - Website data from Google Analytics, Heap, and raw website logs

- Ran A/B & multivariate marketing tests; estimated success probabilities using Bayesian methods and implemented clustering algorithms to identify successful audience characteristics
- Defined, calculated, and analyzed trends in company marketing metrics to forecast sales and revenue
- o Collaborated with reinsurance partner to define and implement a digital insurance API

Senior Investor Analytics Manager at LendingClub

San Francisco, 2016 - 2017

LendingClub was one of the first fintech peer-to-peer lenders. It offers personal loans through an online marketplace, which lowers interest rates for borrowers. It has provided more than \$35 billion in loans since 2007.

- Winner, LendingClub Hackathon, April 2017 for implementing a hybrid gradient boosting tree/logistic regression machine learning model in Python to predict loan default. Outperformed investment returns on platform-wide portfolio by 2% annually.
- o Extensive big data research, reporting predictive modeling, and visualization using Python
 - Analyzed historical forecast vs. actual loan default rates for report to the LendingClub Board of Directors
 - Evaluated statistical significance of client portfolio deviations from platform
 - Designed and implemented a report to track monthly portfolio investment metrics
- Improved onboarding experience for new clients by developing an analytical process to illustrate how loan purchase patterns could impact investment returns in new portfolios

Consulting Actuary at Milliman

Chicago, 2010 - 2016

Milliman Financial Risk Management provides institutional hedging and risk management services to insurance companies and asset managers. It currently manages \$145 billion in assets.

- Managed a team of three to operate <u>variable annuity dynamic hedging</u> programs covering \$10 billion in assets. Developed stochastic financial models to forecast complex cash flows; monitored all sources of risk on a daily basis; reported to client senior management and Boards of Directors.
- o Led a team that launched three managed risk mutual funds with over \$700 million in assets
- o Led a team that developed an innovative financial planning application for iPad and web
- Actuarial consulting projects including valuing M&A transactions and developing investment strategies

Skills

- "An Excel wizard" colleague at LendingClub
- Python: data analysis with pandas and numpy, machine learning with scikit-learn, data visualization with matplotlib and altair, probabilistic modeling with scipy and pymc3, and many API integrations
- Measuring advertising effectiveness by incorporating data from marketing and CRM products such as Facebook ads manager, Google Adwords and Analytics, Heap, and Hubspot
- o Data collection, organization, storage, and schema design with Python and SQL
- Financial performance attribution and variance analysis, complex derivative pricing with Black
 Scholes and Monte Carlo methods, greek calculation, cash flow and reserve calculation for future liabilities
- Website development with html, css, and static site generators like pelican and jinja2
- Confident and enthusiastic public speaker; clear and effective communicator

Education

Northwestern University

2009

Bachelor of Arts, Mathematics

Contact <u>Email</u> <u>Phone</u> <u>LinkedIn</u> <u>Twitter</u> <u>Github</u>